DEISE JP GONÇALVES

GENOMICS DATA SCIENCE

CONTACT



deisejpg@gmail.com



(512) 669-1318 Ann Arbor, MI



linkedin.com/in/deisegoncalves



github.com/deisejpg kaggle.com/deisejpg

PROFILE

Bioinformatics scientist with four years of experience developing advanced algorithms for data analysis, specializing in NGS pipelines and variant detection. Experience designing and implementing algorithms to extract meaningful signals from biological datasets, including NGS data processing, curation, annotation, and statistical modeling. Excels in collaborative teams with opportunities for independent work and multi-directional mentorship.

EDUCATION

PhD in Computational Biology, 2019

The University of Texas at Austin [TX]

Masters in Plant Biology, 2013 State University of Campinas [Brazil]

Bachelor of Science, 2009

Federal University of Uberlandia [Brazil]

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Python, R, Bash, PowerShell, SQL (SSMS)
- Algorithms for NGS analysis and variant detection (classic and custom software)
- Azure (data processing, analytics, storage)
- High-Performance Computing on-prem, TACC (Stampede, Lonestar)
- Generative AI prompting, RAG, embeddings, and LLM training
- Statistical modeling and probability
- Git, Slack/Discord, PowerBI
- Scientific communication and writing

EXPERIENCE

Bioinformatics Scientist at BioIVT, 2022-present

Bridges the communication of data-driven biological findings and business strategy insights between the company's leadership and departments such as clinical data, lab operations, quality assurance and compliance, and global sales teams.

Current Projects

- Proposing and implementing an innovative NGS biomarker portfolio, integrating custom pipelines optimized for QC and structural variant detection
- Working with leadership to explore NGS, slide images, and clinical data assets as a product
- Exploring Generative AI for data wrangling focusing on extracting and grouping relevant tests, treatments, and medications from free text in large clinical datasets
- Developed an NGS pipeline that significantly reduced variant detection and annotation processing time and ensured reproducibility of biospecimen molecular annotation

Postdoctoral Researcher, University of Michigan, 2020-2022 Conducted analyses to detect structural variants for evolutionary genomics (NSF project, publication).

Past Projects

- Developed and implemented various pipelines for assembling and analyzing diverse NGS datasets, including transcriptomes, nuclear target capture data, and organelle genomes
- Collaborated on projects analyzing venom evolution in snakes and developing an analytical tool to optimize NGS data processing
- Developed a method to explore organelle genome variants

Leadership and service

- Received multiple awards and grants that funded research that resulted in various publications
- Instructed advanced bioinformatics in one of the most prestigious workshops in the field, the Workshop on Molecular Evolution at MBL (2018-2022, except during pandemic years)
- Dean's Council Student leader at the UT Austin College of Natural Sciences and the Dept. of Integrative Biology
- Co-organized the Austin Chapter of PyLadies (Python meetup, 2018); member of [WoC]code (2022)